Women of Color Collection, 1903-1992
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Minorities collection
1903-1992
MS 439
4 boxes (1.75 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
The Women of Color Collection consists primarily of published material relating to the status of women of color in the United States. Includes printed materials, bibliographies, position papers, the Indian School Journal, unpublished position papers from the Wesleyan College Center for Research on Women, A Resource Guide of American Indian-Alaskan Native Women, and reports from conferences on the educational and occupational needs of Black, Hispanic, Asian-Pacific-American, and American Indian women.
The Women of Color Collection consists primarily of published material relating to the status of women of color in the United States. For the purposes of this collection, "women of color" is used as a "solidarity definition," indicating (in the words of Loretta Ross) "a commitment to work in collaboration with other oppressed women of color who have been 'minoritized.'"
Materials in the collection date from 1903 to 1992, with the bulk of the material ranging from 1968 to 1982. Types of materials include articles, pamphlets, newsletters, bibliographies, position papers, and clippings. Items of particular interest include an issue of The Indian School Journal, published by the U.S. Indian School in Chilocco, Oklahoma, 1926; a selection of publications related to American Indian/Alaska Native women put out by the Ohoyo Resource Center in Wichita Falls, Texas, 1981-82; unpublished position papers from the Wellesley College Center for Research on Women, 1980-82; A Resource Guide of American Indian-Alaskan Native Women and reports from conferences on the educational and occupational needs of Black, Hispanic, Asian-Pacific-American, and American Indian women, published by the U.S. Department of Education, 1976-80.
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The collection is open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection without further restrictions.
Additions to the Collection
Periodic additions are expected and may not be reflected in this record.
History of the Collection
The Women of Color Collection is an on-going collection comprised of materials purchased by and donated to the Sophia Smith Collection by various donors
Search Terms
African American women--Social conditions--History--20th century; Asian American women--Social conditions--History--20th century; Civil rights--United States--History--20th century; Ethnicity--United States--History--20th century; Hispanic American women--Social conditions--History--20th century; Indian women--United States--Social conditions--History--20th century; Minority women--United States--History--Sources; Minority women--Education--United States-- History--20th century; Minority women--Employment--United States-- History--20th century
- General 1903-1984, undated (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
- The Minority Woman in America: Professionalism at What Cost?, proceedings of a conference at the University of California, San Francisco1979 March 16-18 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Morena 1992 Calendar, Women of Color Resource Guide1992 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- "Moving Mountains Past, Present, and Future: The Role of Women of Color in the American Political System," Brown Papers, National for Women of Color, issue 1, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- The Organizer, National Alliance Against Racist and Political Oppression1981-1983 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Racism 1973, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
- African-American women1979 March 16-18 (Box 1)
  - General1913-1984, undated (Box 1, Folder 8-11)
  - Bibliographies
    - General1955-1978, undated (Box 1, Folder 12-13)
    - Black Lesbians: An Annotated Bibliography, compiled by J.R. Roberts and foreward by Barbara Smith, Naiad Press1981 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - "Black Women Calendar"1981-1983 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Black Women's Educational Policy and Research Network Newsletter1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - In the Memory and Spirit of Frances, Zora and Lorraine: Essays and Interviews on Black Women and Writing, edited by Juliette Bowles, Howard University Institute for the Arts and Humanities1979 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Wellesley College Center for Research on Women: Working Papers1980-1982 (Box 2, Folder 2-3)
- Asian Pacific American women
  - General1957-1978, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Conference on the Educational and Occupational Needs of Asian-Pacific-American Women, U.S. Department of Education1976 August 24-25 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Hispanic and Latina women
  - General1974-1980, undated (Box 2, Folder 6-7)
  - Conference on the Educational and Occupational Needs of Hispanic Women, U.S. Department of Education1976 June 29-30 and 1976 December 10-12 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - La Raza, 1971, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Indigenous women
  - Generalundated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Conference on the Educational and Occupational Needs of American Indian Women, U.S. Department of Education1976 October 12-13 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - The Indian School Journal, Chilocco, Oklahoma1926 February (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - "Native Women" issue of Canadian Women's Studies/les cahiers de la femme, volume 10, numbers 2 and 31989 summer/fall (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Ohoyo Inkhana: A Bibliography of American Indian-Alaska Native Curriculum Materials, Ohoyo Resource Centercirca 1981 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Ohoyo Makachi: Words of Today's American Indian Women, a first collectoin of oratory by American Indian/Alaska Native women, Ohoyo Resource Centercirca 1981 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Ohoyo One Thousand: A Rsource Guide of American Indian Alaska Native Women, Ohoyo Resource Center1982 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Resource Guide of American Indian-Alaska Native Women, edited by Owanah P. Anderson and Sedelta D. Verble, U.S. Department of Education1980 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- OVERSIZE MATERIALS
  - The White Brute, by Mary White Ovington1915 (Box 4)